

Marco Virgolin

Spadinalaan 213, 1031 KB, Amsterdam 🏫

+31 628 735 831 📞

marco.virgolin@gmail.com

marco-virgolin-8815a667 in

@marcovirgolin 🛂

marcovirgolin (7)

https://marcovirgolin.github.io

I am a **senior data scientist** at INGKA, in the **digital ethics and responsible AI** team. I design and develop architectures to make powerful technology such as **large language models** behave in a safe and controllable manner. In the past, I have also worked on **symbolic regression**, **neural architecture search**, and **human-machine interaction**.

Core skills

- Strong analytical thinking & problem solving
- Conceptualization, execution, and supervision of machine learning research projects
- Develop. of libraries & pipelines, benchmarking
- Communication & presentation skills
- Pragmatic, flexible, result-oriented

Experience

MAR 2023 - ONGOING

Senior data scientist / Ingka – IKEA, Amsterdam, NL

I work in the **digital ethics and responsible AI** team. Our team's focus is on making **data** and **AI processes trustworthy** and **accountable**, as well as **designing and training** new valuable, explainable-by-design **AI models**. My current focus is on the research, design, and development of methods to control **large language models**.

SEP 2021 - MAR 2023

Researcher (tenure track) / CWI, Amsterdam, NL

I worked on the intersection between **evolutionary optimization** with machine learning, including **deep learning** (transformers, CNNs). I also studied methods to explain black-box ML models, such as **counterfactual explanations**. Besides this, I was involved in education and supervision (M.Sc. and Ph.D. students), as well as **international scientific collaborations**.

JUN 2020 - AUG 2021

Postdoc / TU Chalmers, Gothenburg, SE

I worked on making **natural language processing** more interpretable, and compared with **large language models**. I also worked on making interpretable ML more personalized with **active learning** and **human-machine interaction**.

NOV 2019 - MAR 2020

Project researcher / CWI, Amsterdam, NL

Project on emotion recognition from facial expression for children. Since pediatric data is scarce, I worked on data augmentation via contrastive learning for deep CNNs.

AUG 2012 - SEP 2013

Web developer / Promoscience, Padriciano, IT

Part-time job during my M.Sc. studies. Being a small company, I wore many hats: from **front-end** to **back-end web development**, incl. building **REST services** and interfacing with **relational data bases**.

Education

JUN 2020

Ph.D. in Evolutionary ML / TU Delft, Delft, NL + CWI, Amsterdam, NL

Design and application of **information theory-based evolutionary algorithms** for learning interpretable **symbolic regression** models. The project application concerned **pediatric radiotherapy**.

MAR 2015

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering / University of Trieste, Trieste, IT

Graduated **cum laude**. Courses ranging from theory of computability and complexity, to software engineering for web apps, IoT. Thesis on natural language processing via genetic programming, later published as a paper.

Honors

- Won SIGEVO Best Ph.D. Dissertation award in 2020, HUMIES Silver award in 2021, 2×Best paper awards
- Served in the program committee of several conferences and workshops: GECCO, ECML-PKDD, PPSN,
 Trustworthy and Socially Responsible Machine Learning Workshop @ NeurIPS, Workshop on eXplainable
 Knowledge Discovery in Data Mining @ ECML-PKDD, and more
- Served as a reviewer for several international peer-reviewed journals: Machine Learning, IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation, Soft Computing, and more
- Invited in 2022 to be an evaluation committee member for the Dutch Research Council in the domain Science
- Recipient as co-applicant of a 300,000 SEK grant by Area of Advance Health Engineering, TU Chalmers 2021
- Recipient of 3 ACM Student travel grant during my Ph.D.
- Gave talks and invited lectures at multiple venues, incl. conferences, University of Amsterdam, TU Delft, MIT

Coding experience

Languages, from proficient to rusty: Python (incl. Pandas, Scikit-learn, PyTorch, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Jupyter Notebooks), C++ (incl. Boost and SWIG to interface C++ with Python), C# (incl. ASP.NET), Java (incl. Android development), Matlab, PHP, SQL (MySQL and SQL Server), Javascript (incl. jQuery, AngularJS, NodeJS)

Examples of different open-source repos (see https://github.com/marcovirgolin):

- <u>GP-GOMEA</u> is a C++ based library which includes several symbolic regression algorithms with a Scikit-learn
 Python interface. These algorithms were found to be among the best performing in <u>SRBench</u> (NeurIPS 2021),
 a large benchmarking platform (which I co-authored and help maintaining).
- Robust-counterfactuals is a Python repository to simulate perturbations that may invalidate counterfactual explanations (a popular explainable AI method) and includes interfaces to experiment with different counterfactual search algorithms and machine learning models.
- **genepro** is a (documented) Python library that I prepared for TU Delft students for the course *Evolutionary Algorithms* of 2021-2022. It contains examples for **classification**, **regression**, and **reinforcement learning**.

Other info

- I was a **co-organizer** of the <u>Joint Lectures on Evolutionary Algorithms</u> (JoLEA), in particular I prepared and maintain the website, and I set up a MailChimp account for mailing lists and tweets.
- I served in ASTRO (2014-2015), a volunteering association for helping with care for hospitalized children.
- An academic version of my CV is available on my website.
- In my free time I enjoy bouldering.